Lewisohn mss., 1922-1937 LMC 1653
Lilly Library
Lewisohn mss.
1922-1937
1960
1961
1962
Lilly Library
LMC 1653
1 Box 1 standard
The Lewisohn mss., 1922-1937, consist of letters from literary men to Ludwig Lewisohn, 1883-1955, author and critic, and personal letters from Lewisohn to his wife, Mrs. Thelma (Spear) Lewisohn, and her mother, Mrs. Elias Spear.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Ludwig Lewisohn was an author and critic. Born in Berlin, Germany, he emigrated to the United States in 1890. Lewisohn is also known for his translations of literary works.
Scope and Content Note
The letters in the collection from literary men contain principally polite comments on Lewisohn's work, occasional criticism, and personal news. Two letters, September 2, 1933 and n.d., from Ezra Pound to Lewisohn relate to payment for work of his to be used in a Lewisohn anthology.
Lewisohn's personal letters to his mother-in-law contain occasional references to his business affairs, and those to his wife concern their courtship and periods when he was away from home on lecture tours.
Among the ms. fragments by Lewisohn in the collection are: "The Defeated," a one page fragment from his The Island Within, December 7, 1926; "Homeward Road," being Part III of An Altar in the Fields, November 19, 1933; and early chapters of his Mid-Channel, October 19, 1920. Included also are carbon copies of corrected typescripts with ms. notes of two undated sonnets, "Thinking how Sophocles, with sounding mask" and "Our joy will hold...through our deliverer Bill" by William Ellery Leonard, 1876-1944, poet and professor of English at the University of Wisconsin; and undated ms. corrections and additions by Franz V. Werfel for his Der Weg der Verheissung.
Correspondents represented in this collection include Shalom Asch, Theodore Dreiser, Havelock Ellis, Arthur Davison Fricke, Susan Glaspell, Hugo Hofmannsthal, Basil King, William Ellery Leonard, Thomas Mann, Edgar Lee Masters, Henry Louis Mencken, Ezra Loomis Pound, Elmer L. Rice, Felix Satten, Upton Beall Sinclair, Thelma Spear, Carl Clinton Van Doren, Jakob Wassermann, Arnold Zweig, and Stefan Zweig.
Note on Indexing Term - "Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968": There are letters from Sinclair which contain comments on Lewisohn's work.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 1960, 1961, 1962
Lewisohn, Ludwig, 1882-1955; Lewisohn, Thelma Spear; Spear, Mrs. Elias; Leonard, William Ellery, 1876-1944; Werfel, Franz, 1890-1945; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968
- 1922-1925 (Box 1)
- 1926-1929 (Box 1)
- 1930-1936 (Box 1)
- 1937 (Box 1)
- Glaspell, Susan. To Lewisohn, L., n.d. (Box 1)
- Hofmannsthal, H. H. To Lewisohn, L., n.d. (Box 1)
- Lewisohn, Ludwig. To Lewisohn, James n.d. (Box 1)
- Lewisohn, Ludwig. To Spear, Mrs. Elias n.d. (Box 1)
- Lewisohn, Ludwig. To Spear, Thelma n.d. (Box 1)
- Mencken, H. L. To Lewisohn, Ludwig n.d. (Box 1)
- Pound, E. L. To Lewisohn, L. n.d. (Box 1)
- Sinclair, U. B. To Lewisohn, L. n.d. (Box 1)
- Leonard, W. E. Sonnets, n.d. (Box 1)
- Werfel, F. V.Der Weg der Verheissung, n.d. (Box 1)
- Mid-Channel. "Ms. of early chapters presented to my dear wife Thelma." Paris, October 19, 1920 (Box 1)
- Homeward Road. "Being the third part of An Altar in the Fields, written during the latter months of my dear wife Thelma's carrying our son James Elias...now presented to her as another token of her husband's devotion + love." Paris, November 19, 1933 (Box 1)